a roll let's try yet another one like I
said it was a good conversation so this
has to do with Fitness landscapes and
choices around different strategies and
responses Fitness landscapes so remember
the concept of Fitness landscapes and we
have this notion of Hills we had this
notion as so let me just give it a
imagine XY plane and I'm going to Z
dimension so I'm like creating Hills on
a map and the hill represents the degree
to which the strategy at that point in
the location is fit it survives it's a
good reproductive strategy so superfood
tiger in Paleolithic North America is
sitting on top of a very high hill it's
a peak predator it's an adaptive
strategy ok now when you're in a
particular circumstance you're always
going to be making choices about how you
actually move around that Fitness
landscape if you find yourself at the
base of the hill and you begin the
process of climbing that hill that's
called a hill climbing strategy this is
a baseline called like the fundamental
strategy it's sort of generally the
right thing to do now here's the
interesting point right here's the
extension that I want to make so think
about a SERP tooth tiger it's at the
peak now when you're at the peak you're
an interesting situation because what
ends up happening is if I refer back to
the video that I haven't uploaded yet
but hopefully by the time you watch this
will have already been uploaded about
the distinct division the phenomenal and
the new middle where Linda happening is
as you begin the process of going about
climbing a hill what you end up doing is
finding that the responsiveness of your
phenomenal schema to the Newman reality
that you find yourself in is actually
very effective that's the whole point is
the definition of climbing a hill your
your adaptive strategies are in fact
adaptive and the process of climbing a
hill is a process of refinement it's a
process of making your phenomenal
strategies more quick more efficient
more effective right you're actually
needing to clean out stuff that is
extraneous right you're really
tightening in and kind of an exactly the
same way that if you have a
a telescope exquisitely focused on a
distant star you can actually get real
clarity on that tiny tiny point of light
but you can't see anything else this
happens this is actually just a
fundamental trade-off so what I want to
do some introduced now is maybe a new
concept I'm gonna call it the generator
function of adaptive capacity or the
more generalized adaptive capacity
rather than the specialized adaptive
capacity so what ends up happening is
you have a generator function which is
just sort of raw exploration of
possibility space and then you have the
things that it generates which are your
phenomenal sense making choice making
schema or you can actually feel like
this if you want the generator function
these things kind of come out of it and
if for the saber-tooth Tiger what ends
up happening is that this actually
becomes a waste you don't need to have
the ability to edit and update your
carrying stuff that you don't need to
have and what you do is you just keep
pushing more and more and more into the
surface layer you become all surface you
become perfectly efficient perfectly
mapped exquisitely detailed filigreed no
fat on this surface so that you're the
most effective saber-tooth Tiger which
is perfect unless inhaled the hill
changes right because now you've lost
that thing down here which is the
editing function which changes this
thing up here
these are giving it up in exchange for
local selective advantage so it ends up
happening of course you cannot become
brittle and if you if you have any minor
change in the hill then your adaptive
capacity begins to go down but you no
longer can respond to it your generator
function has been given up and this is a
trade-off right you have these trades
between them if you're all a generator
function and no adaptive strategy then
you know you suck you can't do anything
in the world you're sort of constantly
having to process from first principles
if you're all fundamentally responding
to well-defined scripts then you've lost
general capacity if you would call the
video on thinking and not thinking it's
the same thing it's just a more
fundamental version of that notion now
the the other primary strategy that is
about an evolutionary theory is Valley
crossing right so this is the capacity
to actually go down in local Fitness go
across some adaptive ballet which sucks
from an evolutionary perspective for
some who knows how long or it may
actually be just wandering the desert
but under the expectation at some point
finding another hill over here which is
in fact higher or at least one which you
can climb to a higher point on you can
think about that as the ability in a
great time to take you future potential
large payout take some discount rate
with the possibility of actually
discovering and finding it comparing it
to your instantaneous value of where you
are now and making the choice of
undergoing that longer thing this shows
up by the way and human beings in say
for example the cookie test which I
understand is actually a really really
effective predictor of the degree to
which human beings are able to have life
success as children so you take a child
put them in a room put down a cookie in
front of them ideally a really delicious
cookie and you say hey here's the deal
yeah I'm gonna leave I'm gonna leave
this room and nobody's gonna be here no
but I can see what happens but if I come
back and there's still a cookie here you
get another cookie but if you if you eat
the cookie while I'm gone and feeling
cookie you get but you will be punished
it's okay it's your choice and then you
leave can you see what happens and the
point is that if the kid has the
capacity to Valley cross the arduous
five minutes of being a kid from a
delicious cookie that means they have a
generator function that's able to
actually do things like sense future
value and make discount rates to make a
choice now that doesn't pay off now but
pays off bigger in the future that's a
valley crossing fundamental and of
course anybody who has a valid crossing
capacity and say the age of five may be
able to offer then use that to respond
more effectively to the world so so now
we find ourselves in this generalized
problematic this is the generalized
situation where you have your localized
adaptive capacity you have your
generative function you have the
trade-off between maintaining the
resources and attention and capacity of
the ability for the generator function
to modify upgrade and edit the sort of
the phenomenal schema and/or the
effectiveness and efficiency of the
phenomenal schema and this shows up for
example in the famous s curves that
describe why and how corporations rise
and fall so I'm a early startup I'm
effectively all adapting faster I'm just
generator function of a bunch of smart
people know quite idea exactly who I am
what I'm doing how to do it
I'm creatively exploring my environment
there's the big up bottom of the s-curve
I'm not showing up as winning in any
meaningful way in fact what I'm actually
doing here is I'm Valley crossing but
then I find something that works now if
it turns out that I found a good hill to
say I found search or social media then
I begin the process of actually
converting adapt generator function into
excellence into effectiveness into
efficiency into scripts and schemas that
are able to work well quickly
responsibly at low cost with low error
so then I actually enter into the
accelerating curve of the s-curve and I
get to get what shows up as at a
phenomenal level it shows up as winning
and I actually feel like I'm winning
them generating a trade off I'm
converting my generator capacity into
what my phenomenal signals are telling
me is good and that's actually true my
adaptive capacity is rising up this
curve until roughly about the midpoint
at the midpoint I actually enter into a
very interesting switch and you might
call this the addictive switch to the
delusional switch which is that I'm
actually still getting returned I'm
getting same for example as a
corporation my my profit line is growing
this is actually the point where my
profit line is growing at its biggest
I've no really one market share I've got
a really good at it nobody can compete
so I'm actually generating really really
outsized returns much they've been
golden age but my rate of acceleration
is actually beginning to slow down my
velocity might actually didn't be
increasing but my rate of acceleration
is slowing down at second derivative so
what ends up happening is that line is
starting to get ready to go here it may
not be here yet but it's starting you're
ready to go here and this is that that
moment from the movie the matrix where
lieutenant your men are already dead
you don't know it now you've got a whole
bunch of well-trained well-armed cops
getting ready to go in and fight with
one little girl what you don't know is
you're a saber-tooth tiger and aneasha
it's about to go away you don't know
that you've externalized your
fundamental generator function into what
is
about to become an obsolete set of
schema you just don't know it because
the signaling mechanism that phenomenal
neumann old gap has separated out and
you remember that loop that we had in
the phenomenal numeral conversation that
the signaling mechanisms that actually
are able to come all the way back and
make it conscious that there's something
wrong are dwarfed by the signaling
mechanism happening at the surface I'm
drinking my coke I'm getting what it is
that I need nope I'm getting what I want
so now I'm addicted to my wants I'm
blind to my my underlying needs I'm even
more blind to the fact that I've begun
making choices that take me out of
sovereignty and the top of the curve
begins to happen which means that you
are now in senescence as an organism as
a corporation and you're fragile
meaning that if at any meaningful point
the adapted landscape changes you're not
gonna be able to respond and you will
die